hello everyone and welcome to another
week of whole talk over the week of
February 15
1999 and Happy Valentine's Day to all
the ladies who tune into the show from
me to you
this week Our Guest is Dr Bert Myers who
for nearly 12 years worked with
holographic Medical Imaging at the
Veterans Administration Hospital in New
Orleans Louisiana
Dr Myers worked to develop holography as
a teaching tool with the end result
being three-dimensional holographic
images in medical textbooks
and Dr Myers will be on in just a minute
to tell us about his research
upcoming guests and shows we have Ron
Olsen coming up in two weeks and you may
have already seen Ron's post holography
work with wildlife and portraits I'll be
talking with him about that and also
about his upcoming book to be published
soon
other shows coming up will examine just
how diverse a field holography is with a
show dedicated to holographic sound
recordings which will include a few
incredible sound samples that you will
be able to download and listen to and
also show on how holography and
holographic principles explain the world
around us and the universe in which we
live so we've got quite a few very
exciting weeks coming up and I hope you
tune back in to enjoy them
I had lunch with Steve Michael this past
Saturday in a small town in Pennsylvania
which was midpoint traveling for both of
us so hello to Steve if you're listening
I had a chance to get a look at Steve's
first split Bean laser pointer hologram
and it was absolutely beautiful he did
this using a
14.95 laser pointer and the image
quality was just as good as Holograms
he's made using this 35 milliwatt
spectrophysics he need laser
but more on that on later later show
since we've taken quite a few shows
lately devoted entirely to laser
pointerography so keep tuned for updates
on that
due to many requests I now have all the
past shows from this season as well as
last season up on the web for your
enjoyment and in the future as each show
moves down from one to another I will
post those shows and make them available
to you right away I had planned on using
reruns during the summer each week until
each new fall season starts but now
you've got them all available to you in
one shot so if you click on the link for
past shows you'll see them all posted
there
I've also received a few emails asking
when I
could be interviewed on whole talk and
while I appreciate the interest I don't
have any plans on being a guest anytime
soon
so maybe next season I will be appearing
at the Tinton Falls New Jersey Holiday
Inn Conference Center as keynote speaker
for the central New Jersey Mensa
conference on Saturday evening March 6th
if you'd like to come out to the
presentation send an email along and
I'll return the details to you okay
here's the interview with Dr Bert Myers
I'm not coming back on after the
interview so I'll thank you for tuning
in now and hope you continue to tune in
each and every week for a new holotalk
show but first this quick message and
then right into the Bert Myers interview
would you like to make your own
one-of-a-kind hologram and learn how you
can start making holograms on your own
at the same time you can this and much
more by attending one of Frank the
greatest holography workshops from
beginner to Advanced Frank's got a
workshop that's just right for you from
single afternoon evening or weekend
introductory workshops to Wednesday
evening five-week complete courses and
don't forget his newest Workshop laser
pointer holography located just off the
Northeast Extension of the Pennsylvania
Turnpike and Interstate 78 the studio is
a quick non-stop drive from the New York
Philadelphia and Baltimore Washington DC
areas for more information call the
Studio's toll-free hotline at
1-800-458-3525 and begin your own
Journey with holography today that's
1-800-458-3525 for more information on
attending a Frankie Freitas holography
Workshop today
thank you
for Dr Myers yeah this is Frankie
Freitas how are you oh fine do you have
a few moments yes I do I'd like to talk
to you a little bit about the work that
you did with the holography and the
medical imaging and for the whole talk
show and I'd also like to ask you if you
could tell the listeners a little bit
about the X-ray photography that you did
years ago
uh years ago I in my medical research
studied I'm a surgeon wound healing how
wound heal and I was very interested in
whether the rate that blood vessels grow
into wounds would affect the healing and
whether we could speed it up or slow it
down and our workout techniques of
taking X-rays of the very tiny blood
vessels capillaries and what's called a
microcirculation in looking at those
x-rays some of them look like abstract
art they were resolved lines running all
over the place I thought it might be
interesting to pursue X-rays and art
form
I started x-raying shells and flowers
and just about anything else caught my
fancy developed it into a sort of an art
form I wasn't the first to do it
although I didn't know it at the time
there were already two other people in
the United States doing it and since
then two or three more has taken it up I
see and you've recently begun working
with that again haven't you yeah well I
got in the holography much later
always had a research lab and the my
funding in other words I had no grant
money to hire technicians and do the
work but I had a very nice lab with the
dark room as part of it
and I was looking for something new to
do and I had the strong background in
photography having studied with Ansel
Adams years ago
oh no kidding yeah Back in 1970 wow did
you ever have any of your working
Reader's Digest yes I did the X-ray at
least digested the article on my x-ray
photography sometime in the 80s I don't
remember exactly where yeah I remember
seeing that yeah
I thought it went back a little further
than the 80s but maybe it was the age
considering it's almost 2 000 now the
80s would be almost 20 years ago now
what you were doing with holography is
very interesting I I have a few of the
Holograms that you sent me and I still
exhibit them and well my original
intention was that three-dimensional
images would be better teaching devices
than
conventional ones and the feel had just
started and they were just developing
methods of mass producing the images
by uh what color I had come out with it
for the power of film and the forgot
what you call now the stamped images
oh the embossed homes were around I
thought there was no reason those
couldn't be in textbooks and they would
be better taking devices than the usual
ones
so I set up a lab basically to make
holograms for teaching purposes and
spent about 12 years doing that made
Holograms of Bones and various tissues
classes now you were using continuous
wave yeah I I didn't have a pulse light
although I wanted one I applied for
grants to buy a post laser but never was
never funded so I used that he needs
like everyone else at the time yeah I
remember you writing to me when you were
in your lab that was down at the
Veterans Administration Hospital in New
Orleans right right and you said that
you actually had an air conditioning
unit that was right outside of your lab
right well when I first thought I had
this lab for that wound work and it was
a deal it just happens one of the other
investigators here won the Nobel Prize
and Congress got all excited because the
first time a VA investigated won the
Nobel Prize basically said what do you
want we want to stay in the VA
what will and die so I need space so
they built him a beautiful building and
all the other investigators like me got
space in it oh I see so I had this brand
new space with a documented to do the
X-ray work and I thought I'd just start
doing holograph I took TJ's course it's
Dr Jung in Lake Forest who at the time
was considered the best teacher and with
my background photography I thought I'd
have no trouble making images so I got
back to New Orleans I bought a laser
made a homemade table and for one year
got absolutely no images just blank felt
no kidding and I was really stumped and
finally realized the problem was
immediately below the lab was the main
air conditioning unit for the animal lab
where they kept the dogs and the rabbits
and the Rats it was 120 horsepower motor
that basically was running continuously
it was probably attached to the ceiling
below you right I don't know but it was
obviously shaking the room too I wasn't
aware of I didn't feel to hear it's like
I got no Holograms jeez finally I caught
somebody to swap and laughs with me it
was in the same building but it was at
the other end which wasn't ideal but at
least I was able to get images
and I kept that space for 12 years
now there's a special process that had
to be used for a lot of the items that
you made a hologram of such as well
because of the uh all living things
contain water
and there's a water evaporates the cell
shrink that includes both plants and
animals and human tissue has to be kept
in formaldehyde or something similar or
in rocks
and as long as it submerged in the prep
preservative it'll keep indefinitely but
if you take it out like to put it on a
hologram table it would dry out quickly
and you'd have nothing
there is another way of preserving
tissue I would actually discovered by a
German pathologist in which he put the
tissue in a very high vacuum and
literally sucked all the water out of
the south then replaced it with a resin
of plastic
so that the final product was
essentially water free and fairly rigid
it looked like the original specimen
except some of the color was gone
and he claimed they would last in half
forever no kidding he called the
technique plastination and a lot of labs
around the world do it United States
there's one main one that's in Mercer
University in Macon Georgia okay and I
was able to get through what happened
was the man that
did the question eight specimens use
them for teach well they they do last
forever but they're not indestructible
if you hand them out to medical students
they would wear away yeah so about 20
years before he had the idea of making
Holograms of the specimens and using the
Holograms as a teaching Divine he had
applied for an NIH Grant was turned down
basically he forgot about meanwhile
years later one of my ex-residents at
LSU North became chairman of the
department of surgery at MRSA and
mentioned there was someone new
orleansville in medical holography and
the other guy remembered and he got us
together and
so he started sending me his specimens
which I would make the Holograms on send
them back so I was able to get good
Holograms of human specimens cancers and
various things yeah had another funny
story I he retired and told me he didn't
know if the school was going to replace
him so I was looking for another source
of specimen that I got on the web and
somebody from Montreal wrote back that
he he did bless the nation too
so I email them Woody lend me the
specimens and he said yes but only
during the summer because we do use them
to teach against the students and such
so I said find mail me two or three next
summer get him back for school he said
I'll do better I'll bring them there I
said well you don't have to do that he
said well I'd like to see New Orleans
that's a good excuse
so he arrives and I got two shots one he
didn't speak English
was a French you know one of the Quebec
and said don't Pride themselves you know
I mean he knew English but it was
beneath him yeah yeah it's big of course
he did speak English and we we were able
to communicate he gave me three
specimens that I kept them were able to
have it now if someone's out there
listening to this show that does
holography and they'd like to do some of
these medical images is it very
expensive to order some of these uh I
don't know I don't think any of sold oh
I see I could give you this Marcel he
could just I don't know if my friend who
was supposed to retire has been replaced
but it's Department of pathology
Mercer University School of Medicine
Macon Georgia
that's enough address and if someone's
doing it he may be glad to lend them too
yeah so the images that you sent to me
were very nice
I think you sent the inside of a heart
to me well I made maybe a hundred in the
12 years you know they were good I had a
lot of others that were you know not so
bright why do you think that there was
never funding for this it seems like it
would be like a very well interesting
aspect well my feeling I just truly
could not get anybody else interested in
there another me I would I even gave
some to my own medical school I gave him
a framed hologram had to track light
with 100 watt house involved in it to
display it free and they wouldn't even
hang it up like you see that is just I
just can't even comprehend that yeah
well that's you you're one of the few
optimists in the field most of the
people I talked to had similar
experiences to mine nobody is really
interested you know you go to a meeting
they say gee that's pretty but that's
the end of it yeah yeah he was actually
a company that was manufacturing a
holographic viewer for medical images as
well actually that was called voxel yeah
voxel yeah they had a great idea they
could take any image on magnetic tape
that CTS and laws
sonograms whatever
and that was in slices like all them are
and put all the slices into one hole
over so you had one sheet of film which
had a full 3D image of the what the
technique showed and they were beautiful
they had worked the Technic it's a man
named Stephen Hawk who was actually an
astronomer from Australia or no England
I think that name was Jackson and he he
worked the technique out and got he got
funding he even went public they sold
stocking yeah and for a while it looked
like they were doing great at least the
stock went up for a little while
then the problem they had their idea was
to sell hospitals and machines to make
the home now they had made some they had
the hospital so send them the magnetic
tag either by mail or if you had a fast
data line I think they call it ISDN line
yeah I think would send the CT to the
California thing and they would make the
Hologram in 24 hours and send it back
air Express
and doing that they were able to make
beautiful images then they would they
were a stock company trying to make
money and their idea was to sell a
machine to do this on site and they
spent five years and on how many
millions of dollars but never got the
machine to work the usual problems I
think motion they had not whoever made
the machine form had never made a
holography it made photographic copying
machines and they didn't realize how
strict the vibration control had to be
but that's my opinion that's not what
they do yeah yeah
the dark sweater with motion for 12
years but the sad thing is that bankrupt
now
I don't know what if anything's going on
but they're in the Los Angeles area and
I was there about a year ago they were
still open but I heard that they're not
now but I can't swear though yeah but
things were all right for them as long
as they were doing the Imaging right
it's when they started to think about
manufacturing the machines well that was
their idea from the beginning yeah last
I talked to Steve he said he realized he
made a mistake they should have just
kept with the images and not try to
Market a machine but it's too late for
that and I think unless maybe they're
starting over again
what was your assistant's name that
worked in your lab for a while I cannot
remember her name the assistant
holographer that you had there for a
while she was an artist
there was a young girl named Madeline
Foust yes who was really a sculptor she
wanted to learn a lot as an art form and
she worked with me really as a Helper
and but doing her own images but she at
the time was single and had to earn a
living as an artist which is virtually
impossible
although I think she was a capable of it
anyway after we had maybe 20 good images
we had a show at the most prestigious
Art Gallery in the world and big crowds
good reviews but we did not sell one
evidence and that discarded her because
she was looking at it you know a way to
earned money and she kind of quit after
that yeah
although she was still interested she
just didn't make any more did you say at
one point that you were trying to do
Holograms using the diodes
I had the idea of when the diodes first
came out
I since I had originally studied with TJ
I kind of kept in touch with him and
never had a question I'd call him and I
asked him can you make Holograms with
these new cheap dials and he said no
and that I didn't even pursue what I
thought
he said you probably could if you had a
power supply to keep to get a coherent
beam out of a dial he thought you needed
a very constant power supply yeah and he
estimated to build a power supply would
cost more than the
helium meal I don't know if he was
apparently he was wrong because you did
yeah we are we're actually all in shock
over this to tell you the truth well
it's the real Improvement for the
average person to be able to make a
hologram with a ten dollar
s later yeah Steve Michael just reported
last week that he was able to uh make an
H1 and H2 copy so now we know that we
can even do split Beam holography with
the diodes
but they're incredibly stable very very
stable I shot a beautiful eight by ten
reflection hologram using uh the little
799 laser pointer and it's beautiful has
about eight inches of depth to it well
I'm glad you know you'll pursuing it I
what finally had in the man I the space
I had in the research building is really
different people with grants yeah and I
applied for five different grants and
was always turned down the
administration said well you can keep
your space until somebody with a brand
needs it you know well that happened
last year a guy had a really brilliant
idea of doing Gene manipulation in space
not only in zero gravity thinks work
differently and he got a big Grant from
NASA I think yeah he needed display so I
got evicted which I really couldn't
complain I had 11 years of free rent
yeah but when when you take into
consideration the crazy things that
grants are given out for well you never
know what what will be worthwhile 20
years you know that's absolutely
incredible I'm really sorry that you had
such a hard time trying to uh trying to
get some support with the work that
you've done because it's beautiful work
well I gave all the lasers and tables to
a local University so at least
somebody's using it yeah well hopefully
they're using it I don't think they're
using it they I gave it to the physics
department and they were not interested
in making you know images for jilling
they were interested in teaching
students the principles of why yeah and
once I visited see what they were doing
when they were making Holograms of
mirrors showing that the Hologram had
the property of the mirrors you know
convex concave and flat which was kind
of an interesting project I would never
thought of doing but do you think you
were just ahead of your time and that
you're going to see a lot of Medical
holography in the future no there's a
lot of interested in 3D imaging in
medicine but it may not be it might be
how high if it might be computers
stereograms I don't know which way it's
going but
I think there will be some 3D imaging
now although I can't say that the
history of that the first
Three Day images the member of The View
Master a little round
with a man that invented that apparently
got family Wealthy on it anyway when he
retired he offered his services to
Stanford University in Palo Alto
and they made I think like 5 000
stereograms of medical specimens for
teaching but they had the same problem
nobody was interested in her
they even they tried to sell them they
even put out on a CD-ROM now you can buy
it be a whole Anatomy course in 3D but
that that and the people that run that
aren't those but except for them that's
about it and all the field of medicine
what are you doing now are you back with
your X-ray photographer well I'm
thinking about retiring from medicine
and doing x-ray photography full-time
but probably won't for a year or two my
health is still good and I enjoy working
and teaching you worked with Jeff Murray
didn't you
yeah well written I went to Jeff when I
got my first facial filter I couldn't
get that to line up I heard about you he
had a school in San Francisco actually
was in Petaluma yeah yeah and oh the
phone he said well I think I can teach
you in three days how to work that thing
so I went out there and learned a line
of special film and I stayed friendly
with Jeff he he had he's out of the
field too I think yeah actually I just
heard today that he may be or is
partnering with someone in New England
foreign
the most practical person in all TJ
knows the theory but how to make some uh
I found uh Jeff much more easy to talk
to yeah he's a great guy just a great
guy I've got to get him on the show
well if you can find him let me know his
address I'd like to keep in touch okay I
will do that well Dr Myers I want to
thank you very much for being on the
show it was very interesting to hear
about your work and I'd like to let the
whole talk listeners know that we not
only have audio this week but we've got
videos well because Dr Myers actually
produced
did about three videos on medical
holography didn't you I think I have
three separate videos of yours yeah well
the last one was the best one I kept
trying to improve it yeah and it got
shot up with each one so the last one's
about nine minutes
most people were born with that the last
one just explains what the uses of yeah
that's going to be on the web as well
and you'll see a link for that right on
the whole talk page below the link where
the whole talk show and you can watch at
Dr Myers's video on medical holography
Dr Myers thank you very much and uh good
luck I'm glad you Frank is still in the
field doing new things like the laser
emitting diodes and because I still
think there's hope for the field just
hope somebody else gets interested in
him with like five or ten of us in the
United States yeah well I'm having a
great time with I feel like a kid all
over again it's like a whole new age of
Discovery for me because it's a whole
new road ahead
take care fine thank you